<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Divyessh's Blog - Linux</title><link href="https://divyessh.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://divyessh.github.io/feeds/linux.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://divyessh.github.io/</id><updated>2020-08-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Why Ubuntu</title><link href="https://divyessh.github.io/why-ubuntu.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-15T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-08-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Divyessh Maheshwari</name></author><id>tag:divyessh.github.io,2020-08-15:/why-ubuntu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Story&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to make this post insteresting, I will start from a story. Long long ago there lived two carpenters. There main proffesion was building houses with kitchens. One of them was named Ubuntu and the Other was named Windows. They both made simmilar houses but they show their actual …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Story&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to make this post insteresting, I will start from a story. Long long ago there lived two carpenters. There main proffesion was building houses with kitchens. One of them was named Ubuntu and the Other was named Windows. They both made simmilar houses but they show their actual art in the kitchens. Ubuntu used to make the kitchen for free. the customers could custimize the front look of the kitchen. All the processes were open and you knew all about your kitchen like what process is going on and what stuff are you getting in kitchen. You basically had all access to it. No one else can bring any foreign material in kitchen without your consent. Now the windows xharges for all the services provided. It provides a very beautifull but not very flexible outlook. It hid all the processes by a beautifull wallpaper. You did not know most of it. Foreign materials are not checked that well. But it was easy to handle as you just had to initialize a process. But on the same note it was really difficult to debug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now think of yourself as a chef and choose which kitchen would you like to have?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Techy terms&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now to make this post related to technology I will elaborate the same story above. Think kitchen as the OS, houses can be the machines (they are mostly same) and the chef as the you yourself. So now I being a developer would personally choose the kitchen made by ubuntu as it is always good to know about your machine and what is going in in your machine. But you may not be a developer. You maybe willing to have a system which can have all accounting compatible applications or can have all the proofreading stuff. You may not be focused about the proccesses but the main applications that you need to use. I totally agree with you for your decision of choosing windows. But if you are a developer and speciallly python, then I would like to ask one single reason for choosing windows over Ubuntu (or other Linux distributions). There are so many li raries whose dependencies can not be installed in windows. You can not use so many commands. If your program has problems then you can never find the error without getting your head shook. So why not Linux??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Mistake I made&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also used Windows initially and when I shifted on Linux it was a completely different and better experience. As a developer you dont need looks you create looks. Well if you want to give it a try, install it as a bootable so that your windows data is not lost. You might have a shock while restarting it, but its fine it is just telling you what it is doing to open your system and start using it. I do not have a comment section yet but you can surely email me at
divyesshm@gmail.com 
and tell me your opinion or we can interact on my social media handle. Soon it will be in the social media section. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Linux"></category></entry></feed>